<casaxml xsi:schemaLocation="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/casa.xsd file:///opt/casa/code/xmlcasa/xml/casa.xsd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/psetTypes.html">



<task category="information" name="makemask" type="function">

  <shortdescription>Makes and manipulates image masks</shortdescription>

  <description>Construct masks based on various criteria, convert between mask-types, and generate a mask for clean</description>

  <input>

    

    <param name="mode" type="string"><shortdescription>Mask method (list, copy,expand,delete,setdefaultmask)</shortdescription><description>Mask method (list, copy,expand,delete,setdefaultmask)</description>
      
      <value>list</value>
      <allowed kind="enum">
        <value>list</value>
        <value>copy</value>
        <value>expand</value>
        <value>delete</value>
        <value>setdefaultmask</value>
       
      </allowed>
    </param>




    

            
            <param subparam="true" name="inpimage" type="any"><shortdescription>Name of input image.</shortdescription><description>Name of input image.</description>
            
            <any limittypes="string stringArray" type="variant"/>
            <value type="string"/>
            </param>

            
            
            <param subparam="true" name="inpmask" type="any"><shortdescription>mask(s) to be processed: image masks,T/F internal masks(Need to include parent image names),regions(for copy mode)</shortdescription><description>mask(s) to be processed: image masks,T/F internal masks(Need to include parent image names),regions(for copy mode)</description>
            
              <any limittypes="string stringArray" type="variant"/>
              

              <value type="string"/>
            </param>

            <param subparam="true" name="output" type="string"><shortdescription>Name of output mask (imagename or imagename:internal_maskname)</shortdescription><description>Name of output mask (imagename or imagename:internal_maskname)</description>
               
               <value/>
            </param>

            <param subparam="true" name="overwrite" type="bool"><shortdescription>overwrite output if exists?</shortdescription><description>overwrite output if exists?</description>
               
               <value>False</value>
            </param>

            
      <param subparam="true" name="inpfreqs" type="any"><shortdescription>List of chans/freqs (in inpmask) to read masks from </shortdescription><description>List of chans/freqs (in inpmask) to read masks from </description>
              
              <any limittypes="string intArray" type="variant"/>
              <value type="intArray"/>
            </param>

      <param subparam="true" name="outfreqs" type="any"><shortdescription>List of chans/freqs (in output) on which to expand the mask</shortdescription><description>List of chans/freqs (in output) on which to expand the mask</description>
              
              <any limittypes="string intArray" type="variant"/>
              <value type="intArray"/>
            </param>

           




            
            
            

            
            



    

            <constraints>

                <when param="mode">
                    <equals value="list">
                        <default param="inpimage"><value type="string"/></default>
                    </equals>
                    <equals value="copy">
                        <default param="inpimage"><value type="string"/></default>
                        <default param="inpmask"><value type="string"/></default>
                        <default param="output"><value type="string"/></default>
                        <default param="overwrite"><value type="bool">False</value></default>
                    </equals>
                    <equals value="expand">
                        <default param="inpimage"><value type="string"/></default>
                        <default param="inpmask"><value type="string"/></default>
                        <default param="inpfreqs"><value type="intArray"/></default>
                        <default param="outfreqs"><value type="intArray"/></default>
                        <default param="output"><value type="string"/></default>
                        <default param="overwrite"><value type="bool">False</value></default>
                        
                    </equals>
                    <equals value="delete">
                        <default param="inpmask"><value type="string"/></default>
                    </equals>
                    <equals value="setdefaultmask">
                        <default param="inpmask"><value type="string"/></default>
                    </equals>
                    
                    
                    
                    

    </when>

             </constraints>


  </input>

  <returns type="void"/>

  <example>

Modes :
-------------

list : list internal masks in inpimage to the log
copy :  Copy/merge masks and regrid if necessary to a new or existing mask
expand : Expand a mask from one range of freqs to another range
delete : delete an internal mask from an image (if the deleted mask was a default mask,
         the task chooses the first one in the remaining internal mask list (as appears
         in the log when do listing with mode='list')
setdefaultmask : set a specified internal mask as a default internal mask




In all cases (for output mask is expected), if the output image has a different coordinate system from the
result of input and processing, the mask will be re-gridded to the output
coordinate system.


Parameter Descriptions and rules:
------------------------------
inpimage : Name of input image to use as a reference for the output coordinates (if output does not exist).
           Also used as a reference image when regions are specified in inpmask for copy mode
           If output is a new image specified with an internal T/F mask, the pixel values in the input image
           are copied to the output image and the regions specified in inpmask are merged (if mutliple regions
           specified) and treated as a valid region therefore will be UNMASKED in output.
           default: none (must specify for list, copy, expand modes)

Expandable parameters for mode='copy','expand','delete' and 'setdefaultmask':
inpmask : Name(s) of input mask(s)
          default: none
         To specify an image (zero/non-zero) mask, just give a image name (e.g. myimage1.im)
         To specify an internal (T/F) mask, you must give a parent image name and the internal mask name
         separated by a colon. (e.g. myimage1.im:mask0). The internal mask names can be found by running
         the makemask task in mode='list'.

         (expand mode)
         'myimage:mask0' : use(true/false) internal mask
         'myimage'  : use the inpimage values to make a mask (zero/non-zero).
                      Non-zero values are normalized to one in the process.
         (copy mode)
         Specify the image mask(s), T/F mask(s), and region(s) to be merged in a list of strings.
         The regions can be specified directly in the CASA region format or in the text file(s) contains
         the regions.

         (delete and setdefaultmask mode)
         Specify the internal mask with the format, image:mask


output : Name of output image.
         default: none
         *The resultant mask is written as an image (zero/one) mask if the output is a plain image name
         *The resultant mask is written as an internal (T/F) mask if the output name is the form of 'imagename:maskname'
          The created mask is set as a default internal mask.
         *To re-grid a mask to a different coordinate system,
          give an image with the target coordinate system in inpimage. Or make a copy an image
          with the target coordinate system and specified the name of the copy in output.


    - If output is specified as a plain image, if it exists, it will regrid the mask to
      the new coordinate system  and modify output (if overwrite=True).
    - If output is specified as an image with an internal mask, if the internal mask exists,
      it will regrid the mask to the new coordinate system  and modify the internal mask only (if overwrite=True).
    - If output does not exist, it will only copy inpimage.
    - If output == inpimage, do not regrid. Only modify in-place.

    *** Please note that the term 'mask' is used in the image analysis and clean tasks in opposite
        sense. In the image analysis, the masked region in general a region to be excluded while
        clean's input mask defines the region to be used as a clean box/region.
        In the makemask task, since the most common use case of output image mask is to use as
        an input mask in clean, when it converts an internal mask to the image mask,
        the 'masked' region (where the pixels are masked and have the Boolean values 'False')
        of the internal mask is translated to the pixels with value of 0 in output image mask.

overwrite : overwrite the mask specified in output? (see also the output rules above)
            default: False
            * Note that for a cube mask, overwrite=True generally overwrites in the specified channel planes only and
            so any pre-existed masks in other channels  will be remain untouched.

Additional expandable parameters for mode='expand':
  inpfreqs : input channel/frequency/velocity range
             Specify channels in a list of integers. for frequency/velocity,
             a range is specified in a string with '~', e.g. '1.5MHz~1.6MHz', '-8km/s~-14km/s'
             (for the cube with ascending frequencies)
             default: []  - all channels
             * Note that the range in frequency or velocity needs to be specified as the same order
             as in the template cube specified in inpimage. E.g., if a template cube has descending
             frequencies, then the range will be, for example,'1.6MHz~1.5MHz' or '-14km/s~-8km/s'

  outfreqs : output channel/frequency/velocity range
             Specify same way as inpfreqs
             default: []  - all channels


Usage examples :
---------------------------
(1) (list mode):
     makemask(mode='list', inpimage='mymask.im')
     it prints out a list of the internal mask(s) exist in mymask.im to the log

(2) (copy mode):
     Regrid a Boolean mask from one coordinate system to another and save as Boolean mask
     in the output image.

     makemask(mode='copy', inpimage='oldmask.im', inpmask='oldmask.im:mask0', output='newmask.im:mask0')

(3) (copy mode):
     Same as (1), but save as integer mask in the output image.

     makemask(mode='copy', inpimage='oldmask.im', inpmask='oldmask.im:mask0', output='newmask.im')

     * mask0 is translated so that pixels in oldmask.im that appears as 'masked' in the viewer or
       has the pixel mask value = 'False' when extracted in imval, are to have pixel value of 1 in
       the output image, newmask.im.

(4) (copy mode):
     Convert a Boolean(true/false) mask to an integer(one/zero) mask in the same image

     makemask(mode='copy', inpimage='oldmask.im', inpmask='oldmask.im:mask0', output='', overwrite=True)


(5) (copy mode):
     Convert an integer(one/zero) mask to a Boolean(true/false) mask in the same image

     makemask(mode='copy', inpimage='oldmask.im', inpmask='oldmask.im', output='oldmask.im:mask0')

(6) (copy mode):
     Copy a CRTF mask defined in mybox.txt to a Boolean(true/false) mask in a new image

     makemask(mode='copy', inpimage='image1.im', inpmask='mybox.txt', output='image2.im:mask0')

     The pixel values of image1.im will be copied to image2.im and the region outside mybox.txt
     will be masked.

(7) (copy mode):
     Apply a region defined in a CRTF file to mask part of an image

     makemask(mode='copy', inpimage='image1.im', inpmask='myregion.crtf', output='image1.im:mask0')

     The region is copied as a T/F mask (mask0) inside the image, image1.im. The region outside myregion.crtf
     will be masked.


(8) (copy mode):

     Merge a (one/zero) mask and  T/F masks, using the input coordinate-sys of inpimage and
     saving in a new output file. Remember, if the image specified in output already exist and
     has a different coordinate system from inpimage, the mask will be regridded to it.
     All masks to be merged are specified in a list in inpmask.
     The name of internal masks must be given in the format, 'parent_image_name:internal_mask_name',
     as shown the example below.

     In the example below, image1.im (the 1/0 mask), the internal masks, mask0 from image1.im
     and mask1 from image2.im, and a region (on image1.im as defined in inpimage)  are combined.
     The output, newmask.im is a new mask name which has not
     yet exist so image specified in inpimage, image1.im's coordinates are used as a target
     image coordinates. If image1.im and image2.im has different coordinates, image2.im:mask1 is
     regridded before it is combined to the other two masks.

     makemask(mode='copy',
              inpimage='image1.im', 
              inpmask=['image1.im', image1.im:mask0','image2.mask:mask1', 'circle[[15pix , 15pix] ,8pix ]'],
              output='newmask.im);

(9) (expand mode):
     Expand a (one/zero) mask from continuum imaging to use as an input mask image for
     spectral line imaging. Use an existing spectral line clean image as a template by
     specified in inpimage.
     The inpfreqs is left out as it uses a default (=[], means all channels).

     makemask(mode='expand', inpimage='spec.clean.image', inpmask='cont.clean.mask'
              outfreqs=[4,5,6,7], output='spec.clean.mask')

(10) (expand mode):
     Expand a Boolean mask from one range of channels to another range
     in the same image.

     makemask(mode='expand', inpimage='oldmask.im', inpmask='oldmask.im:mask0', inpfreqs=[5,6], outfreqs=[4,5,6,7],
              output='oldmask.im:mask0', overwrite=True)


(11) (expand mode):
     Expand a Boolean mask from a range of channels in the input image to another range
     of channels in a different image with a different spectral-coordinate system.
     Save the mask as ones/zeros so that it can be used as an input mask in the clean task.
     As the inpimage is used as a template for the CoordinateSystem of the output cube, it is
     a prerequisite to have the cube image (a dirty image, etc). In this particular example,
     it is assumed that bigmask.im is a working copy made from the cube image of a previous clean
     execution. It is used as an input template and the resultant mask is overwritten to the same image.

     Specify the infreqs and outfreqs in frequency (assuming here bigmask.im has frequencies in ascending order)
     makemask(mode='expand', inpimage='bigmask.im', inpmask='smallmask.im:mask0',
              inpfreqs='1.5MHz~1.6MHz', outfreqs='1.2MHz~1.8MHz', output='bigmask.im', overwrite=True)

     or to specify the ranges in velocities,
     makemask(mode='expand', inpimage='bigmask.im', inpmask='smallmask.im:mask0',
              inpfreqs=4.0km/s~0.5km/s', outfreqs='6.5km/s~-2.4km/s', output='bigmask.im', overwrite=True)


(12) (delete mode)
      Delete an internal mask from an image.

      makemask(mode='delete', inpmask='newmask.im:mask0')

(13) (setdefaultmask mode)
      Set an internal mask as a default internal mask.

      makemask(mode='setdefaultmask', inpmask='newmask.im:mask1')





  </example>

</task>

</casaxml>