<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" ?>
<casaxml xmlns="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/psetTypes.html"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/casa.xsd
file:///opt/casa/code/xmlcasa/xml/casa.xsd">


  <task type="function" name="wvrgcal" category="calibration">

    <shortdescription>Generate a gain table based on Water Vapour Radiometer data</shortdescription>
    
    <input>
      
      <param type="string" name="vis" kind="ms" mustexist="true">
      <description>Name of input visibility file</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="string" name="caltable" mustexist="false">
      <description>Name of output gain calibration table</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="double" name="toffset">
      <description>Time offset (sec) between interferometric and WVR data</description>
      <value>0</value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="bool" name="segsource">
      <description>Do a new coefficient calculation for each source</description>
      <value>True</value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="stringArray" name="sourceflag" subparam="true">
      <description>Regard the WVR data for these source(s) as bad and do not produce corrections for it (requires segsource=True)</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="stringArray" name="tie" subparam="true">
      <description>Prioritise tieing the phase of these sources as well as possible (requires segsource=True)</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="int" name="nsol" subparam="true">
      <description>Number of solutions for phase correction coefficients (nsol>1 requires segsource=False)</description>
      <value>1</value>
      </param>
            
      <param type="bool" name="disperse">
      <description>Apply correction for dispersion</description>
      <value>False</value>
      </param>
            
      <param type="stringArray" name="wvrflag">
      <description>Regard the WVR data for these antenna(s) as bad and replace its data with interpolated values from neighbouring antennas</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="string" name="statfield">
      <description>Compute the statistics (Phase RMS, Disc) on this field only</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="string" name="statsource">
      <description>Compute the statistics (Phase RMS, Disc) on this source only</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="string" name="smooth">
      <description>Smooth calibration solution on the given timescale</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="double" name="scale">
      <description>Scale the entire phase correction by this factor</description>
      <value>1.</value>
      </param>

      <param type="intArray" name="spw">
      <description>List of the spectral window IDs for which solutions should be saved into the caltable</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="intArray" name="wvrspw">
      <description>List of the spectral window IDs from which the WVR data should be taken</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      
      <param type="string" name="reversespw">
      <description>Reverse the sign of the correction for the listed SPWs (only needed for early ALMA data before Cycle 0)</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>

      <param type="bool" name="cont">
      <description>Estimate the continuum (e.g., due to clouds) (experimental)</description>
      <value>False</value>
      </param>

      <param type="double" name="maxdistm">
      <description>maximum distance (m) of an antenna used for interpolation for a flagged antenna</description>
      <value>500.</value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="int" name="minnumants">
      <description>minimum number of near antennas (up to 3) required for interpolation</description>
      <value>2</value>
        <allowed kind="enum">
            <value>1</value>
            <value>2</value>
            <value>3</value>
        </allowed>
      </param>

      <param type="double" name="mingoodfrac">
      <description>If the fraction of unflagged data for an antenna is below this value (0. to 1.), the antenna is flagged.</description>
      <value>0.8</value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="bool" name="usefieldtab">
      <description>derive the antenna AZ/EL values from the FIELD rather than the POINTING table</description>
      <value>False</value>
      </param>

      <param type="stringArray" name="refant">
      <description>use the WVR data from this antenna for calculating the dT/dL parameters (can give ranked list)</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>
      
      <param type="string" name="offsetstable">
      <description>(experimental) subtract the temperature offsets in this table from the WVR measurements before calculating the phase corrections</description>
      <value></value>
      </param>


      <!-- ================================================================= -->
    
      <constraints>
      <when param="segsource">
        <equals type="bool" value="True">
          <default param="tie"><value type="stringArray"></value></default>
          <default param="sourceflag"><value type="stringArray"></value></default>
        </equals>
        <equals type="bool" value="False">
          <default param="nsol"><value type="int">1</value></default>
        </equals>
      </when>
      </constraints>

    </input>

    <returns type="variant" limittypes="void record"/>

    <description>

Information about the observation and the performance of WVRGCAL is written to the CASA logger
and also returned in a dictionary; see the CASA cookbook for a more detailed description of these parameters.
The dictionary element 'success' is True if no errors occured.

Of particular note is the discrepancy parameter (Disc): high values (> a few hundred microns) 
may indicate some levels of cloud contamination and the effect of applying the WVRGCAL correction 
should be checked; values > 1000 um in all antennas have currently been found to indicate that 
WVRGCAL correction should not be used.

      
  vis -- Name of input visibility file
              default: none; example: vis='ngc5921.ms'

  caltable -- Name of output gain calibration table
              default: none; example: caltable='ngc5921.wvr'

  toffset -- Time offset (sec) between interferometric and WVR data
             default: 0 (ALMA default for cycle 1, for cycle 0, i.e. up to Jan 2013 it was -1)

  segsource -- Do a new coefficient calculation for each source
               default: True

  tie -- Prioritise tieing the phase of these sources as well as possible
         (requires segsource=True)
         default: [] example: ['3C273,NGC253', 'IC433,3C279']

  sourceflag -- Flag the WVR data for these source(s) as bad and do not produce corrections for it
               (requires segsource=True)
               default: [] (none) example: ['3C273']

  nsol -- Number of solutions for phase correction coefficients during this observation.
          By default only one set of coefficients is generated for the entire observation. 
          If more sets are requested, then they will be evenly distributed in time throughout 
          the observation. Values > 1 require segsource=False.
          default: 1

  disperse -- Apply correction for dispersion
             default: False

  wvrflag -- Regard the WVR data for these antenna(s) as bad and use interpolated values instead
             default: [] (none) example: ['DV03','DA05','PM02']           

  statfield -- Compute the statistics (Phase RMS, Disc) on this field only
               default: '' (all) 

  statsource -- Compute the statistics (Phase RMS, Disc) on this source only
                default: '' (all)             

  smooth -- Smooth the calibration solution on the given timescale 
            default: '' (no smoothing), example: '3s' smooth on a timescale of 3 seconds

  scale -- Scale the entire phase correction by this factor
           default: 1. (no scaling)

  spw -- List of the spectral window IDs for which solutions should be saved into the caltable
           default: [] (all spectral windows), example [17,19,21,23]

  wvrspw -- List of the spectral window IDs from which the WVR data should be taken
           default: [] (all WVR spectral windows), example [0]

  reversespw -- Reverse the sign of the correction for the listed SPWs
                (only neede for early ALMA data before Cycle 0)
                default: '' (none), example: reversespw='0~2,4'; spectral windows 0,1,2,4

  cont -- Estimate the continuum (e.g., due to clouds)
          default: False

  maxdistm -- maximum distance (m) an antenna may have to be considered for being part
              of the antenna set (minnumants to 3 antennas) for the interpolation of a solution 
              for a flagged antenna
              default: 500.

  minnumants -- minimum number of near antennas required for interpolation
                default: 2

  mingoodfrac -- If the fraction of unflagged data for an antenna is below this value (0. to 1.), 
                 the antenna is flagged.
                 default: 0.8

  usefieldtab -- derive the antenna AZ/EL values from the FIELD rather than the POINTING table
                 default: False

  refant -- use the WVR data from this antenna for calculating the dT/dL parameters (can give ranked list)
                default: '' (use the first good or interpolatable antenna), 
                examples: 'DA45' - use DA45 
                          ['DA45','DV51'] - use DA45 and if that is not good, use DV51 instead

  offsetstable -- (experimental) subtract the temperature offsets in this table from the WVR measurements before
             using them to calculate the phase corrections
                default: '' (do not apply any offsets)
                examples: 'uid___A002_Xabd867_X2277.cloud_offsets' use the given table

  </description>

  <example>

   wvrgcal(vis='uid___A002_X1d54a1_X5.ms', caltable='cal-wvr-uid___A002_X1d54a1_X5.W',
           toffset=-1, segsource=True, tie=['Titan,1037-295,NGC3256'], statsource='1037-295')

  </example>

</task>

</casaxml>
