<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" ?>
<casaxml xmlns="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/psetTypes.html"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://casa.nrao.edu/schema/casa.xsd
file:///opt/casa/code/tools/xml/casa.xsd">

 
        <tool name="tableindex" module="table">
        <shortdescription>Allows value based table access</shortdescription>
       
<code>
	<include>tools/tables/tableindex_forward.h</include>
<private>
	<include>tools/tables/tableindex_private.h</include>
</private>
</code>

<description>
A tableindex makes it possible to find rows in a table based on their
contents. When constructing the tableindex it has to be specified for
which column or columns an index has to be built. Those columns will
be loaded in memory and thereafter row numbers can be found in a fast way
using a binary search.

<example>
\begin{verbatim}
vis:=table("3C273XC1.MS");
vis.summary();
visinx:=tableindex(vis, "ANTENNA1");
rows:=visinx.rownrs(4);
rows:=visinx.rownrs(4,7);
\end{verbatim}
This example builds an index for column ANTENNA1.
The one but last line returns the row numbers (1-relative) of all rows
with value 4 for ANTENNA1. There after these row numbers can, for
example be used in <link anchor="table:table.getcell.function">getcell</link> to read data.
The last line is similar, but in this case the search interval 4-7 is
given. So all rows with value 4, 5, 6, or 7 in ANTENNA1 are found.
An optional 3rd and 4th argument can be given to tell if the interval
is open or closed (i.e. if the boundaries are part of the interval).
Note that for indices on floating point numbers it is best to use
a search interval, because an exact match on such numbers usually fails.
</example>

<example>
\begin{verbatim}
vis:=table("3C273XC1.MS");
vis.summary();
visinx:=tableindex(vis, "ANTENNA1 ANTENNA2");
rows:=visinx.rownrs([ANTENNA1=4, ANTENNA2=5);
rows:=visinx.rownrs([ANTENNA1=4, ANTENNA2=5), [ANTENNA1=4, ANTENNA2=8];
\end{verbatim}
This example builds an index for column ANTENNA1 and ANTENNA2.
Because multiple columns are used, the arguments for function
<link anchor="table:tableindex.rownrs.function">rownrs</link> have to be records now.
So the one but last line returns the row numbers (1-relative) of all rows
with value 4 for ANTENNA1 and 5 for ANTENNA2.
The last line defines a search interval again. In this case the
ordering of the columns in the index is important. It finds the rows
of ANTENNA1=4 where ANTENNA2 is in the interval 5-8.
</example>

Normally a column used in a tableindex has to be a scalar column.
However, if a single column is used that column can contain arrays.
In such a case the \texttt{rownrs} function finds the rows where
a value in its array matches the given search value.

If all key values in the index are unique, the function
<link anchor="table:tableindex.rownr.function">rownr</link> can be used as well. It returns
a single row number instead of a vector.

</description>

 
   <method type="constructor" name="tableindex">
   <shortdescription>Construct a tableindex</shortdescription>
   
<description>
Construct an index for the given table. The names of one or more
scalar columns forming the index have to be given.
If a single name is given, the column can be an array column too.
Normally a sort will be done to get the key values in the correct order.
If the table is already in the order of the data in the given columns, the
argument \texttt{sort} can be set to F to avoid needless sorting.
</description>
<input>
<!--
     <param type="record" direction="in" name="tab">
     <description>table to be indexed, wants a table tool</description>
     </param>

     <param type="stringArray" direction="in" name="columns">
     <description>column names</description>
     </param>

     <param type="bool" direction="in" name="sort">
     <description>is a sort of the key values needed?</description>
     <value>true</value>
     </param>
-->
</input>
<return type="bool"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="set">
   <shortdescription>Set table and columns to be indexed</shortdescription>
   
<description>
Reset the \texttt{tableindex} tool to index the given table and
columns. It works similar to the tableindex constructor.
</description>
<input>

     <param type="record" direction="in" name="tab">
     <description>table to be indexed, wants a table tool</description>
     </param>

     <param type="stringArray" direction="in" name="columns">
     <description>column names</description>
     </param>

     <param type="bool" direction="in" name="sort">
     <description>is a sort of the key values needed?</description>
     <value>true</value>
     </param>
</input>
<returns type="bool"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="isunique">
   <shortdescription>Are all key values in the index unique?</shortdescription>
   
<description>
T is returned if all key values in the index are unique. In that case
the function <link anchor="table:tableindex.rownr.function">rownr</link> can also be used.
</description>
<returns type="bool"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="setchanged">
   <shortdescription>Tell the index that columns have changed</shortdescription>
   
<description>
When data are changed in an indexed column, the index should be
updated. The tableindex tool recognizes addition and deletion of rows
and updates the index accordingly. However, it does not recognize if data in a
column are changed. This function can be used to tell the tableindex
that data in one or more columns are changed and force it to update
the index. If no column names are given it assumes all columns have changed.
</description>
<input>

     <param type="stringArray" direction="in" name="columns">
     <description>names of changed columns</description>
     <value>all</value>
     </param>
</input>
<returns type="bool"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="rownr">
   <shortdescription>Find the row number matching the search value</shortdescription>
   
<description>
Find the row number (1-relative) of the row containing the given
search value. If no row is found, 0 is returned.
This function can only be used if the index contains unique
key values (thus if <link anchor="table:tableindex.isunique.function">isunique</link>
returns T), otherwise \texttt{rownrs} should be used. 
\\Normally the search value should be given as a record in which the
field names match the column names in the index. However, if the index
is formed from a single column the search value can be given directly
as shown in the examples in the introduction. The data type should be
correct though.
</description>
<input>

     <param type="record" direction="in" name="key">
     <description>search value</description>
     </param>
</input>
<returns type="int"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="rownrs">
   <shortdescription>Find the row numbers matching search values</shortdescription>
   
<description>
Find the row numbers of the rows matching the given search value or
interval. An interval
is given if the \texttt{upperkey} argument is also given. In that case
the 3rd and 4th argument determine if the boundaries of the interval
are inclusive (i.e. part of the interval).
\\As in function \texttt{rownr} the search values must be given as a
record if the index consists of multiple columns.
</description>
<input>

     <param type="record" direction="in" name="key">
     <description>search value</description>
     </param>

     <param type="record" direction="in" name="upperkey">
     <description>end of search interval</description>
     <value>0</value>
     </param>

     <param type="bool" direction="in" name="lowerincl">
     <description>include lower boundary</description>
     <value>true</value>
     </param>

     <param type="bool" direction="in" name="upperincl">
     <description>include upper boundary?</description>
     <value>true</value>
     </param>
</input>
<returns type="intArray"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="close">
   <shortdescription>Close the tableindex</shortdescription>
   
<description>
Close the tableindex. It can thereafter be reused using the set function.
</description>
<returns type="bool"/>
</method>

 
   <method type="function" name="done">
   <shortdescription>End the tableindex tool</shortdescription>
   
<description>
End the tableindex and free up all memory. It cannot be reused anymore.
</description>
<returns type="bool"/>
</method>

</tool>
</casaxml>

